Hey בוקר טוב! Boker Tov! Today's דף Daf is ס"ב. Samech Bet.
Shh,
today's דף Daf is ס"ב. Samech Bet. And by the way, just
to announce, we're still a דף Daf ahead and we're about to
and we're finishing up so we're going to skip Sunday, okay? Everybody
can sleep late on Sunday. So we won't be finished we'll do
we will be finishing נזיר Nazir with the rest of the world
on Monday.
So, we're in the middle of a whole discussion about who is
included and excluded from making this נזירות. Nezirut. The משנה Mishnah includes
women and slaves, it excludes non-Jews,
and the גמרא Gemara is discussing why and basically excludes non-Jews based
on the פסוק Pasuk of דבר אל בני ישראל, Daber el Bnei
Yisrael, right? So therefore the גמרא's Gemara discussing the question about why
non-Jews are not partially included, because by ערכין, Erchin, it also says
דבר אל בני ישראל, Daber el Bnei Yisrael, but it says איש,
ish, what is the פסוק Pasuk is איש כי יפלא נדר בערכך?
ish ki yafli neder beerkecha? And by that we sort of make
a balance and we say non-Jews are partially exclude, partially include. They
can't make an ערך, Erech, if they say, if they take a
vow to give money or whatever in the context of an ערך,
Erech, it's not binding, but if you they can be נערך, Ne'erach,
if a Jew says the value of that person is on me,
even if it's a non-Jew, it still is goes by the tables
in the תורה Torah by the value set in the תורה. Torah.
So it's a middle position by the balance between בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael and איש. ish. So the גמרא's Gemara question is well by
נזיר Nazir it also says בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael and איש ish
and let's find a middle position.
And first it rejected that it said no by non-Jews are clearly
excluded from נזירות Nezirut because it says לאביו ולאמו לא יטמא l'aviv
u'l'imo lo yitama and since they don't have טומאה Tumah it obviously
can't be referring to that. That was like one answer. But then
the גמרא Gemara said you know there's even a better answer, like
there's no logical middle position by נזיר. Nazir. What would be that
middle position? The middle position would let's say be they couldn't bring
a קרבן נזיר Korban Nazir but the laws of נזירות Nezirut would
still be binding on them. But then you wouldn't need we already
know that they can't bring a קרבן נזירות Korban Nezirut from another
פסוק Pasuk that speaks about the fact that non-Jews can bring קרבנות,
Korbanot, but only an עולה, Olah, not a קרבן נזירות, Korban Nezirut,
only a נדבה. Nedavah. So therefore again there would be nothing for
the פסוק Pasuk to be they're being excluded as well from נזירות
Nezirut they must be being totally excluded.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara suggested possible other ways in which maybe
they're excluded partially and included partially, like נזיר שמשון, Nazir Shimshon, like
נזיר עולם. Nazir Olam. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara suggests possible other
ways in which maybe they're excluded partially and included partially, maybe נזיר
עולם, Nazir Olam, maybe נזיר שמשון, Nazir Shimshon, maybe for מדיר את
בנו בנזיר, madir et beno b'nazir, you know, other types of things,
but the גמרא Gemara but the גמרא Gemara basically they said no,
those things are all הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai or whatever,
or they're not written in the פסוקים. psukim. Again, there's no way
once we know they're not bringing a קרבן Korban obviously the only
thing left for the פסוקים psukim to do is to exclude them
completely. That's what the גמרא Gemara where we had ended up. Okay,
but now and now we continue in the top of ס"ב עמוד
א. Samech Bet Amud Aleph. אי הכי Ei hachi says the גמרא
Gemara two lines from the top. אי הכי, Ei hachi, איש כי
יפלא נדר בערכך ish ki yafli neder beerkecha בערכין למה לי? beerchin
lama li? So now we're sort of we sort of have ended
that discussion. We're okay they're totally excluded from נזיר Nazir either because
of לאביו ולאמו לא יטמא l'aviv u'l'imo lo yitama or because there's
no logical middle position. So why says אי הכי Ei hachi the
הגר"א HaGra sort of takes out those words אי הכי. Ei hachi.
Like okay that was the end of that discussion. Period. Fine. They're
fully excluded from נזיר. Nazir. Now let's go back and look at
this discussion we had about ערכין Erchin and understand like this idea
that they're partly included partly excluded. So איש כי יפלא נדר בערכך
ish ki yafli neder beerkecha בערכין למה לי? beerchin lama li? Now
why does it have to say איש ish to include non-Jews partially
by ערכין? Erchin? מכדי Meichti let's take a look. איתקש ערכין לנדרים
Ha'itkish Erchin m'nedarim and an ערך Erech are linked to a נדר.
Neder. דאמר קרא איש כי יפלא נדר בערכך. d'amar Kra ish ki
yafli neder beerkecha. If you make a vow of בערכך beerkecha of
paying the ערך Erech of value of somebody and then you go
by those amounts that are set in the תורה, Torah, okay? So
ערך Erech is a type of a נדר Neder it's explicitly linked
and we already know ותניא v'tanya we taught by נדרים Nedarim גבי
נדרים gabei Nedarim איש מה תלמוד לומר? ish ma talmud lomar? Why
does it say איש? איש Ish ish איש ish? לריבוי l'ribui or
it doesn't say איש איש ish ish I think it just says
איש ish one. Hold on. ויקרא כ"ב. Vayikra Kaf Bet.
I think it's איש ish then it's איש לרבות.
ish l'rabot. Yeah or something like that. But just anyway. Oh no
it does say I'm sorry it does say איש איש. ish ish.
דבר אל אהרן ואל בניו ולאמר ואל כל בני ישראל ואמרת אליהם
איש איש מבית ישראל ומן הגר בישראל אשר יקריב קרבנו לכל נדריהם
ולכל נדבותם אשר יקריבו לה' לעולה. Daber el Aharon v'el banav v'leimor
v'el kol Bnei Yisrael v'amarta aleihem ish ish mibeit Yisrael u'min hager
b'Yisrael asher yakriv korbano l'chol nidreihem u'l'chol nidvotam asher yakrivu l'Hashem l'olah.
All right.
So it's ironic because on the one hand it says twice it
says מבית ישראל ומן הגר mibeit Yisrael u'min hager and we say
no איש איש ish ish even means non-Jews. But also but again
לעולה l'olah that non-Jews can make a נדר Neder like a free
will type of an offering a קרבן Korban an עולה Olah and
so on. So איש איש ish ish no no no it's not
a נדר Neder like this loaf of bread is אסור עלי. asur
alai. When we talk about non-Jews make נדרים Nedarim we're talking about
קרבנות Korbanot ערכין Erchin things that are like types of vows that
translate into something that a gift to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
something that is given.
Once we see גר ger as a גר צדק? ger tzedek?
No yeah it's a גר צדק ger tzedek standard גר ger is
yeah. Okay ומן הגר u'min hager גבי gabei certainly גר ger גבי
ישראל gabei Yisrael and so on. איש איש. ish ish. לרבות את
העובדי כוכבים lerabbot et ha-ovdei kochavim שנודרים נדרים ונדבות כישראל. she-nodrim nedarim
u-nedavot ke-Yisrael. Okay,
so we already know that they can make vows and again this
is not most of the vows that we talked about in like
מסכת נדרים, masechet nedarim, this is more like קרבנות korbanot types of
things. לעולה. le-olah. But also it would include a vow of giving
money to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and a vow of ערכין.
erchin. So that's already implicitly included. We know they can make ערכין.
erchin. Okay. כי יפלי בערכך איש כי יפלי בערכך למה לי? ki
yafli be-erkecha ish ki yafli be-erkecha lama li?
So why does it have to say איש ish to include non-Jews
by ערכין erchin if I already know that they can? Now there's
also like a hidden question here which is what we said yesterday
was that non-Jews can't do ערכין. erchin. They can't make the vow
of ערכין. erchin. They can only be vowed but they can't make
the vow. They can be the object, not the subject. Here, if
it's based on the idea that they can make a נדר, neder,
right, and it says we don't even need the פסוק pasuk by
ערכין, erchin, presumably it's saying that they can be the one making
the vows. So there's sort of like a double question: why do
we need איש ish and also it seems that they can even
make the vows by ערכין? erchin?
I think you need איש איש ish ish versus איש. ish.
Maybe, but let's see what the גמרא gemara says. Okay. אלא האי
איש מיבעי ליה. ela hai ish miba'ei leih. So the איש ish
by ערכין, erchin, you're right. You don't need the איש ish by
ערכין erchin to say that they can be in the פרשה parsha
of ערכין. erchin. That we already know from this issue of נדר.
neder. So why do I need the איש כי יפלי נדר בערכך?
ish ki yafli neder be-erkecha?
Why do I need it by ערכין? erchin? So אלא האי איש
מיבעי ליה לאתויי מופלא סמוך לאיש. ela hai ish miba'ei leih le-atuyei
mufla samuch le-ish.
Somebody who can be מופלא, mufla, which is כי יפלי, ki yafli,
is a vower essentially or is near being an adult, near being
a man. Okay, which means that there is a principle which we
maybe have referred to only once or twice, it's funny we've gone
through all of נדרים Nedarim and נזיר Nazir and only referred to
this principle maybe once or twice, but there's actually a principle, it's
a משנה mishna in נדה Niddah and so on, that
a boy or girl a year before their age of majority, בר
ובת מצוה bar u-bat mitzvah respectively, if they make a vow then
you give them a little test and you see if they know,
it says נדריהם נבדקים. nidrehem nivdakim. You check and you see: do
you know what the vow means? Do you know what it means
to make a vow to God and so on? And if they
basically know לשם מי נדרו, leshem mi nadaru,
they would know, if they know for the sake of whom, for
God, I mean I presumably it means like, you know, little kids
talk about God, but presumably it means like the weight and the
significance of making a type of a vow to God. If they
understand that, then their vow is binding even a year before. Okay,
and there's an interesting question: like is that a דאורייתא de-oraita principle
or דרבנן derabbanan principle? We're about to introduce it. If it's a
דאורייתא de-oraita principle, where do we get it from? So one version
is: the extra איש כי יפלי. ish ki yafli. On the one
hand, איש ish means an age of majority, but somehow the כי
יפלי, ki yafli, the combination of איש כי יפלי ish ki yafli
is telling us if the vow is a meaningful vow even before
that age of majority it can be binding. Now it doesn't mean
if you have the וילנא גאון Vilna Gaon and he's five years
old, it's still not binding, okay? It still requires a certain age
of majority, but it's that year before. So somehow it's some combination
of tradition and a read of the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so and
it works for נדרים, nedarim, but it would work for anything that's
under הפלאה. hafla'ah. So it would work for presumably נזיר Nazir and
making קרבנות korbanot and all the types of stuff that we said
in מסכת נדרים, masechet nedarim, you know, הקדש, hekdesh, all those types
of things that are part of הפלאה, hafla'ah, word acts, speech acts
that create a change of status. Okay, so once again, if we
already know that a non-Jew is in the פרשה parsha of נדרים,
nedarim, of making vows, especially when it comes to קרבנות korbanot or
giving things to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, why do we need
איש ish by ערכין? erchin? And it says we don't need איש
ish by ערכין erchin to include non-Jews, we need איש ish by
ערכין erchin for this other principle. It's really איש כי יפלי ish
ki yafli for this principle of מופלא סמוך לאיש. mufla samuch le-ish.
So now
the גמרא gemara says הניחא למאן דאמר מופלא סמוך לאיש דאורייתא. ha
nicha le-man de-amar mufla samuch le-ish de-oraita. That's good if that's a
biblical principle, so that we learn it from this פסוק. pasuk. אלא
למאן דאמר דרבנן, ela le-man de-amar derabbanan, but if it's only a
rabbinic principle, so obviously that's not what the פסוק pasuk of איש
כי יפלי ish ki yafli is telling me. So איש כי יפלי
למה לי? ish ki yafli lama li? So what's איש כי יפלי
ish ki yafli telling me? So the גמרא gemara says לאתויי מופלא
סמוך לאיש דעובדי כוכבים. le-atuyei mufla samuch le-ish de-ovdei kochavim. That would
tell you fine, it doesn't apply to Jews. This principle of מופלא
סמוך לאיש mufla samuch le-ish is rabbinic when it applies to Jews,
but איש כי יפלי, ish ki yafli, איש ish is including
non-Jews as what we said before, but we said oh non-Jews we
know already are in the פרשה parsha of ערכין. erchin. No, but
the combination of איש כי יפלי ish ki yafli means that non-Jews
can make a vow even before the age of majority. So it's
very ironic, right? There's no concept of מופלא סמוך לאיש mufla samuch
le-ish by Jews, but there is a concept. by non-Jews. Okay, now
תוספות Tosfos asks this question. Well, I'll tell you why I think
it does make sense. First we'll look at what תוספות Tosfos says.
If you take a look at תוספות, Tosfos, so
on the it's back on ס"א ע"ב, Samech Aleph Amud Beis, the
like last of the near like right before the lines get the
widest, איש כי יפלא דכתיב בערכין למה לי בעיא עד דחמי להיות
נערים. Ish Ki Yafli Dechishiv Be'erchin Lami Lei Ba'ei Ad Dechami Lihyos
Ne'arim. I'm sorry, not that one.
Okay, הניחא, Haniacha, excuse me, the תוספות הניחא, Tosfos Haniacha, four lines
from the bottom. הניחא למאן דאמר במסכת נדה דאורייתא אלא למאן דאמר
דרבנן מאי איכא למימר ואתויי מופלא סמוך לאיש בעובד כוכבים מדרש תמיה
הוא דבישראל לית אלא מדרבנן. Haniacha Leman D'amar Masechet Niddah De'oraisa Ela
Leman D'amar Derabbanan Mai Ikka Lemeimar V'asuyei Mufle Samuch L'ish B'oved Kochavim
Midrash Teima Hu D'v'yisrael Leis Ela Miderabbanan.
This concept of מופלא סמוך לאיש Mufle Samuch L'ish is only rabbinic
by a Jew ובעובד כוכבים איתא, V'v'oved Kochavim Issa,
and by non-Jews, it's a biblical principle. ופירש ר"י דודאי ישראל דלא
הוי בכלל בל יחל עד דהוי גדול. U'perash Ri D'vadai Yisrael D'lo
Havei Bichlal Bal Yachel Ad Dehavei Gadol. No,
it does make sense because a ישראל Yisrael until he's an adult,
the מצוות Mitzvos don't apply to him. So the prohibition of בל
יחל דברו, Bal Yachel Devaro, don't violate your words, don't apply to
him until he is בר או בת מצוה, Bar or Bas Mitzvah,
he or she is בר או בת מצוה. Bar or Bas Mitzvah.
וכי הוי גדול מיד איתא בבל יחל, V'chi Havei Gadol Miyad Issa
B'Bal Yachel,
and once they become an adult, then those prohibitions of violating vows
apply. דרשינן כל דלית בבל יחל לית בהפלאה כדאמר בפרק יוצא דופן
מייתן ממופלא סמוך לאיש. Darshinan Kol Deleis B'Bal Yachel Leis B'Haflaa K'd'amar
B'Perek Yotzei Dofen M'atyan Mimufle Samuch L'ish.
So therefore, since the מצוות Mitzvos about נדרים Nedarim don't apply yet,
we could say that the binding nature, the you know the act
of the vow is not meaningful yet. It doesn't create any reality
because the מצוות Mitzvos don't apply yet. So you're in a like
you're in a you know you're not yet it's clear you're not
fully yet in the category because the מצוות Mitzvos don't apply so
you can do nothing. אבל עובד כוכבים שאינו ראוי לבוא בכלל בל
יחל. Aval Oved Kochavim She'eino Ra'uy Lavo Bichlal Bal Yachel. But a
non-Jew that never will be prohibited by בל יחל, Bal Yachel, he's
not those מצוות Mitzvos are not relevant to him. This gets to
the point we said before that there's a question about the meaning
of the acts of a non-Jew even when they're not about being
legislated, even when they're not explicitly being addressed by law, we still
have to ask like what are the meaning of those acts. So
non-Jews are not it's funny they can make a vow
and they don't have to keep it.
They don't have to keep they wouldn't violate. Now where the relevance
would still be, if they make a vow to give something to
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and they're under our jurisdiction,
we would force them to keep it. You know it's a binding
vow and you have to keep it. Or you know there might
be some like metaphysical reality. There's still a reality of breaking a
vow, you know, even if they didn't violate a particular law. There's
something like when you don't want to break a promise, right? Is
it because somebody you're it's legally obligated for you to keep your
promise? So there could be a metaphysical reality, but there's not a
legal reality. So therefore לא שייך למעוטי. Lo Shayach Limu'atei. There's no
logic like oh well they shouldn't be yet in the פרשה Parsha
because by a Jew you can say you're not yet fully in
the פרשה, Parsha, you're not yet legally bound by this. But by
a non-Jew where that's not even a relevant concept, so therefore it
can start even earlier, it can start even before the age of
majority. So that's what תוספות Tosfos says and that makes a good
deal of sense. Let me try to sort of say my idea
which could be seen as an elaboration of תוספות's Tosfos idea. Before
I do, I just want to point out an interesting question which
תוספות Tosfos and the גמרא Gemara maybe is taking for granted, but
maybe this is also what's being questioned, is that there's a concept
of age of majority by non-Jews. And now what is that age?
Is it 13? Is it 18? Is it 20? Who knows what?
Meaning within the הלכה Halacha of שבע מצוות בני נח, Sheva Mitzvos
B'nei Noach, right? If a non-Jew steals at the age of
five, is that is he prosecuted? You know what is the age
of majority? You could have מופלא סמוך לאיש Mufle Samuch L'ish meaning
the period before majority, but there's still an open question well what
is that age of majority? Right? And I don't know, is it
בר ובת מצוה, Bar and Bas Mitzvah, is it some other age?
So that's one question. But I want to say another point which
I think elaborates a little bit on what תוספות Tosfos is saying,
which is
that even within the law
the laws of שבע מצוות בני נח Sheva Mitzvos B'nei Noach there
is much less formalisms and quanta sort of quantifiable definitions
by שבע מצוות בני נח. Sheva Mitzvos B'nei Noach. For example, right,
גזילה Gezeila for Jews is only a שוה פרוטה, Shaveh Prutah, less
than a שוה פרוטה Shaveh Prutah you don't transgress. For non-Jews it's
even פחות משוה פרוטה. Pachos Mishaveh Prutah. Now you know there are
reasons that they say well they're not מוחל Mochel on פחות משוה
פרוטה Pachos Mishaveh Prutah etc. but that seems to be like not
really the issue. I'll give you another example which is a parallel,
okay? Abortion. For Jews it is you know whatever it is it's
not murder. Okay there's a whole range of opinions from רב משה
Rav Moshe who says it's just below murder to those that say
like it's almost nothing and whole range of question about what stage
of a fetal development but it's not murder.
Okay based actually on a פסוק Pasuk in last week's פרשה Parsha
which says שופך דם האדם באדם דמו ישפך. Shofech Dam Ha'adam Ba'adam
Damo Yishafech. איזהו אדם באדם? Eizehu Adam Ba'adam? What's a person inside
of a person? It's a fetus. And by non-Jews it's included in
the in the prohibition of לא תרצח. Lo Tirtzach. So what's going
on there? And you can't say it's a difference between the fetus
because it doesn't matter if a Jew is aborting a non-Jew's fetus.
it's not it's not לא תרצח lo tirtzach and if a non-Jew
is aborting a Jew's fetus, it is לא תרצח. lo tirtzach. So
it's not about the fetus, it's about what the law is telling
you, you have a different law for Jews and for non-Jews. And
it seems that the difference is, is that somehow for שבע מצוות
בני נח, sheva mitzvot bnei noach, you don't have these sort of
formal lines of distinction, right? The idea is that you're saying, well,
you know, life is only after this point and not before that
point, whereas by non- or money is only after this amount of
money, that amount is not really considered money, right? And somehow by
שבע מצוות בני נח, sheva mitzvot bnei noach, I can't explain further
what the logic of this is, but somehow by שבע מצוות בני
נח, sheva mitzvot bnei noach, we don't draw those lines, any amount
of money, any amount of life, right? We don't make sort of
these types of of types of distinctions. So in a similar way
you could say, and this is now my question about the issue
of the age of majority, do we make do we make draw
a line and say at this age you're an adult and at
this age you're not? Or would we say, you know, we'll check
case by case? This kid this kid violated, let's see how intellectually
mature they are, you know, and whether they are somebody that can
it makes sense to think that they are yet, you know, responsible
for their actions. But we don't have a formal definition, oh, this
age automatically this way and less than automatically on the other side.
Whatever you say in general about שבע מצוות בני נח, sheva mitzvot
bnei noach, that's completely consistent with the גמרא's Gemara idea that מופלא
סמוך לאיש mufla samuch le'ish applies to בני נח bnei noach and
not to Jews. Because by Jews it's like, no, we have בר
מצווה. bar mitzvah. What do you mean? Before בר מצווה bar mitzvah
whether it's legally binding let's test you. Where do we ever hear
in הלכה halacha that you do a case by case analysis to
see if you fall in the category or not? We have formal
rules. Look it up, how old are you, right? I mean, so
therefore, the idea that we'll assess case by case, you know, that's
a weird idea, but by by in terms of normal הלכה, halacha,
we go by a a formalism. But by non-Jews, who says that
there's any age of majority? And even if there is an age
of majority, let's maybe it can be also modified by looking at
the individual cases without these sort of formal definitions. So I think
that this is really very consistent with differences that we find between
like הלכה halacha and how הלכה halacha understands שבע מצוות בני נח.
sheva mitzvot bnei noach.
Do you go for טעם כעיקר ta'am ke'ikar or do you just
go by שישים? shishim?
You mean you mean for the way we do it. Yeah, that's
even אשכנז. Ashkenaz. אשכנז Ashkenaz but that's a good example, do you
taste the food or do you just go by שישים? shishim? I
mean that's even going one step closer to non-Jews.
הספרדים hasfaradim are much closer to non-Jews.
Alright, yes,
but we
are saying though that מופלא סמוך לאיש mufla samuch le'ish even by
בני ישראל bnei yisrael you do.
But we're working within the possibility that that's only דרבנן. derabbanan. It
says if מופלא סמוך לאיש mufla samuch le'ish is only דרבנן, derabbanan,
what's it doing? Oh, so it's saying מופלא סמוך לאיש mufla samuch
le'ish for non-Jews. So this is the question, why would this be
only דרבנן derabbanan for Jews and דאורייתא de'oraita for non-Jews?
Oh, but wait wait in general you're saying, you're saying it's more
מחמיר machmir by non-Jews, this is one of them?
Yeah, that's not as interesting of an answer. Okay, so what תוספות
Tosafot says is, well for Jews it makes sense it's דרבנן derabbanan
because you're not yet bound by בל יחל. bal yachel. And what
I'm doing is I'm maybe what to be seen as a broader
explanation of תוספות, Tosafot, which is it's not just you're not bound
by בל יחל, bal yachel, it's that by Jews the whole formal
categories is what fundamentally matters. Okay, whereas by non-Jews we don't go
by those fundamental categories and therefore we're going to look at it
case by case.
Are you saying so much more strict?
I understand, you said strict, I don't find that as interesting an
answer.
Just different formal categories, one might be by the Jews it might
be age and by the non-Jews it might be cognitive ability. It's
not that they lack formal- Well,
no, I think my point about formal is is that there are
criteria but it's not as like just you know very it's not
as easy it's not as it's not as the things that are
sort of measured case by case and they're not as quantifiable and
as observable and as arbitrary to me seems to be like what
I would call less of a
formalism, right?
Whether a child is measured on a חינוך chinuch point or not,
is that a formal is that a formal measure or not?
No, that's not. That would be a good example of something that's
not, but that also raises a question about, you know, חינוך chinuch
okay, that's that is a good question. חינוך chinuch is one example,
but I will tell you if you look at some of what
the פוסקים poskim say by חינוך, chinuch, they start ignoring those assess
case by case and they start trying to come up with concrete
ages. There's this consistent push to concretize and to take out of
contextual assessment that that happens in הלכה. halacha. Okay, but you're right,
I mean you still need definitions, you can't have a law system
without definitions but what's is how contextual is it or not. Okay,
so yeah, one last point.
One last thing? Did anybody raise the point about is there any
problem of non-Jews who are not really praying to our God or
praying to another God and they're coming to our temple and making
a נדר?
neder? Right, so presumably the נדר neder has to be, so they
can bring the קרבן korban to our God. Now, are we חושש
choshesh that they're thinking that they're offering at temple in to our
God and having in their mind like עבודה זרה, avoda zara, you
know, I don't know, I don't remember any you know it's clear
that they're doing it that they can bring a קרבן. korban. Look,
within a pagan world, they can accept our God amongst their whole
pantheon of gods, right? If they completely reject our God and think
that they're tricking us and giving us to offer and it really
is going to their god, like I don't know of any source
that talks about that, but they can. don't have to necessarily be
acknowledging.
Oh, but I mean, but right, meaning yeah.
Yes, I don't think that any sources at least that I can
think of indicate that when they offer sacrifices they have to reject
other gods. But you know, they understand there's a Jewish God and
they're sending this sacrifice to be offered to the Jewish God. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: אלא ela *Ella*.
Okay, so that's one thing we could do with איש כי יפלי
ish ki yafli, *Ish ki yafli* מופלא סמוך לאיש mufla samuch l’ish
*muflas samuch l'ish*, either for ישראל *Yisrael* or for a non-Jew. One
of the other, one way or the other, it's telling us מופלא
סמוך לאיש mufla samuch l’ish, *muflas samuch l'ish*, איש כי יפלי ish
ki yafli, *ish ki yafli*. So now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says
like this: הניחא *Hannicha* says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*... wait a minute...
הניחא *Hannicha*... okay, הניחא למאן דאמר בני ישראל נערכין ואין עובדי כוכבים
נערכין *Hannicha leman de-amar Bnei Yisrael neerachin ve-ein ovdei kochavim neerachin*. That's
good if the difference between Jews and non-Jews by ערכין erchin. *Erchin*
is: are you the object of the ערך *Erech*? Are you נערך
*neerach*? You know, that your value is the one that is being
assessed. So that, if that applies only when you say ערך *Erech*
of this Jew, as opposed to ערך *Erech* of the non-Jew. יכול
לא יומרין *Yachol lo yumarin*, maybe non-Jews can't be the subject, can't
be the ones to make the ערך *Erech*? תלמוד לומר איש ish
שפיר *Talmud lomar ish shafir*. So now we get to what was
implicit in today's whole discussion, but not what we said yesterday, that
it sounds like from so far what we've been talking about, that
the non-Jew can make an ערך *Erech*, right? Because it says, 'well,
why do I need a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* to tell me he's
an ערכין erchin? *Erchin*? I already know he can make a נדר
neder *neder*'. Which sounds like he can make an ערך *Erech*, right?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says actually what we said yesterday was
a debate. Everybody agrees that non-Jews are partially excluded from ערכין erchin,
*Erchin*. The question is from which category of ערכין archin *Erchin*? From
making the ערך *Erech* or from being נערך *neerach*? So the discussion
today assumes that they make the ערך *Erech*. A: It says we
learn it out from the נדרים nedarim *nedarim*. B: It wants to
tell us a principle about מופלא סמוך לאיש mufla samuch l’ish *muflas
samuch l'ish*. מופלא סמוך לאיש mufla samuch le'ish, *muflas samuch l'ish* is
about your age for you to be able or you know to
make the ערך *Erech*. So all of that works very nicely if
they can make the ערך *Erech* and somehow they just can't be
נערך *neerach*. Okay. Now that's good for what we've been saying so
far. אלא למאן דאמר בני ישראל מעריכין ואין עובדי כוכבים מעריכין *Ella
leman de-amar Bnei Yisrael maarichin ve-ein ovdei kochavim maarichin*. But if you
say that בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael* are the ones that make the
ערך *Erech*, not non-Jews. יכול לא יהיו נערכין *Yachol lo yihyu neerachin*,
maybe non-Jews can't be נערכין *neerachin*? תלמוד לומר איש *Talmud lomar ish*,
even so איש *ish* is coming to include that they're נערכין *neerachin*.
Okay, so if that's true, that's not relevant for מופלא סמוך לאיש
*muflas samuch l'ish*. אפילו תינוק בן חודש בערכיהו *Afilu tinok ben chodesh
barucheihu*. So even a one-month-old is already in the category of the
people that can be the object of the ערכין *Erchin*. So איש
כי יפלי ki yafli, *ish ki yafli*—who. כי יפלי למה לי ki
yafli lama li? *Ki yafli lamli*? So what's כי יפלי ki yafli,
*ki yafli* coming to tell me? Now before we even answer that,
we have to point out the irony, right? Even though according to
this approach, which is what we said yesterday, now we see it's
debated, even though a non-Jew can make a נדר neder *neder*, can
give a קרבן korban, *korban*, can presumably be מקדיש *maqdish* his car
to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*, you know, can be
מקדיש קרבנות *maqdish korbanos*, somehow according to this approach, he's excluded from
making an ערך *Erech*, from this particular category that says when you
say 'the ערך *erech* of this person is on me' and you
look up their age and their sex and you determine how much
you pay, right? That's a particular פרשה parsha *parsha* of the תורה
*Torah*. That category they can't do. They can't, you know, obligate themselves
in that vow. All other נדרים nedarim, *nedarim* they can make; that
vow they can't do. That's what we're saying right now. Okay? Yes?
Sorry, but they can make it on somebody else? They can be
the object of it. If I say 'the ערך *Erech* of that
non-Jew'—but not the subject of it. Okay? So up until this point
we were assuming they can be the subject and not the object.
That's consistent. That's איש כי *ish ki*—מופלא סמוך לאיש *muflas samuch l'ish*,
they can make a נדר neder. *neder* etc. Now we're suggesting even
though they can make a נדר neder. *neder* and all that good
stuff, for some reason they cannot be the מעריך *maarich*, the subject
of ערך *Erech*. Okay? It's an arbitrary exclusion. All right. But if
you do say that, besides it being a weird exclusion, what do
you do with the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* about איש כי יפלי ki
yafli. *ish ki yafli*? What's it coming to include? Okay. So let's
take a look. So, כי יפלי ki yafli למה לי *ki yafli
lamli*? אמר רב אדא בר אהבה *Amar Rav Adda bar Ahva*: לאתויי
עובד כוכבים גדול דאף על גב דגדול הוא אם אינו יודע להפלות
*L'asuyei oved kochavim gadol d'af al gav d'gadol hu im eino yodea
lehaflot*. So here it is, this is so perfect according to the
whole framework I put out before. Of course I knew this was
coming, but I really believe in the framework I put out before.
It's telling you that this actually is coming to tell you not
to include something but to exclude something. איש כי יפלי ki yafli
*Ish ki yafli*, even if you are an איש *ish*, only if
you know what you're doing, only if you're יודע להפלות *yodea lehaflot*.
If you do not know, even if you're an adult, if you
do not understand the meaning of your act of הפלאה hafla'ah. *haflaah*,
it is not binding. And that is only true by non-Jews. For
a Jew, we do not do a case-by-case assessment and not only
that, even if you say, 'Yeah, I didn't know'—let's say, I don't
know, I mean, if you don't have, let's say, a proven cognitive
disability, you know, and you go and you enter into a business
deal and then you say, 'Yeah, but I didn't understand what it
was about' or whatever, it's like, tough luck buddy, you know. You're
an adult. You know, we, that, unless, again, unless you can really
prove like a significant cognitive disability, like, it doesn't matter. You don't
check, you know, you don't check case-by-case. But if you're a Jew
and you said, yeah, I said המקדש amaktish, my car, but I
didn't know what I was talking about, I didn't really understand, it's
like, tough luck. You're an adult. You're המקדש, amaktish, end of story.
But if you're a non-Jew and you do it, then you don't
care about the age, and you just look at whether you know,
whether you were of, whether you really understood what you were doing.
So again, it's a perfect example about whether, on the one hand,
even if you're under the age of majority, assuming there is an
age of majority for non-Jews, if you're under that age and you
know what you're doing, it's binding, which is not true by Jews,
at least, you know, assuming מופלא סמוך לאיש is דרבנן. d’rabbanan. And
if you're over the age and you don't know what you're doing,
it's not binding, which is also not true by non-Jews. It's a
case-by-case assessment regardless of any line of majority, and by Jews it's
consistently this more formal category. But nevertheless, you know, since as what
we're talking about, if they say they know what they were doing
and go to חכם chakham and get it מותר. matir. Oh right,
so there's a way to undo it through a separate process, but
it doesn't mean fundamentally it wasn't binding. Okay. So that's what it's
coming to. Now the funny thing is though, one minute, but you
just said they're not in the פרשה parsha of ערכין. So how
could you say it's coming to say that even if you know
that even if you're an adult, if you didn't know what you
were doing fundamentally they can't do an ערכין? So it doesn't matter,
you know or not know, you're an adult or not adult. So
תוספות Tosafot basically says, all right, what we're going to do here
is we're going to apply this principle to all the other things
a non-Jew can do, all the other נדרים nedarim. that a non-Jew
can do. So even though they're excluded from ערכין, they can make
a קרבן, korban they can be המקדש, they can do other types
of נדרים, nedarim and there it would not matter if they're an
adult if they didn't know what they were doing. Okay. So we
have a very nice sort of conceptual, now of course it could
have said that before in the opposite direction, anyway, we have a
very nice now conceptual idea that by Jews it goes by majority,
בר ובת מצווה, bar v’bat mitzvah, maybe there's a year before that
it's contextual, that's debatable, but non-Jews, it fundamentally has nothing to do
with an age of majority. If you're young and you know what
you're doing, it's binding, and if you're old and you don't know
what you're doing, it's not binding. Okay. So that's what we say
here. אלא כי יפלי דכתיב רחמנא, ela ki yafli d’chtiv rachmana, so
that's what we do by כי יפלי, ki yafli basically to tell
me at least for non-Jews it goes by knowing what you're doing
and not by the age. Now the גמרא Gemara continues: אלא כי
יפלי דכתב רחמנא גבי נזירות למה לי. ela ki yafli d’chtav rachmana
gabei nezirut lama li. So now what we learned out this idea
from כי יפלי, ki yafli מופלא סמוך לאיש, you know again, by
non-Jews or or younger and knowing what you're doing, older and not
knowing what you're doing, one thing or the other we learned out
from כי יפלי. ki yafli But it also says it by a
נזירות. nezirut. Right? What's the פסוק pasuk by a נזיר? nazir? It
says כי יפלי לנדור נדר נזיר. ki yafli lindor neder nazir. So
what does that כי יפלי ki yafli, telling me? It's funny, we
started today by talking about what does איש tell me, now we've
switched our emphasis to what does כי יפלי ki yafli, tell me?
All right, anyway, אלא says the גמרא, Gemara אלא כי יפלי דכתב
רחמנא גבי נזירות למה לי מכדי איתקש נזירות לנדרים. ela ki yafli
d’chtav rachmana gabei nezirut lama li michdi itkash nezirut l’nedarim. So נזירות
nezirut is linked to נדרים. nedarim. איש כי יפלי לנדור נדר נזיר.
ish ki yafli lindor neder nazir. So anything that we learn from
כי יפלי by נדרים Nedarim about מופלא סמוך לאיש by a Jew
or a non-Jew, we apply to נזירות. nezirut. So כי יפלי למה
לי? What's כי יפלי telling me by a נזיר? nazir? לאתויי ידיים
שאינן מוכיחות, l’atuyei yadayim she’einan mochiachot, to include the case of hands,
handles, which are not evident. Okay, this you might remember this from
the beginning of נדרים. nedarim Okay. דאיתמר ידיים שאינן מוכיחות, d’itmar yadayim
she’einan mochiachot, what if you have a handle that is not self-evident
what it means? Okay, like the example by נזירות nezirut is, you
know, the נזיר nazir is walking in front of you and you
say אהא, ehei, I will be. So do you mean I will
be, you know, or you hold on to your hair and you
say אהא, ehei, do you mean I'll be a נזיר, nazir, do
you mean like I'll get a haircut or something? Okay. So a
יד yad is because you didn't say a full sentence, you said
like a partial sentence, an elliptical, it was a handle, it sort
of, you know, it was referred to something else, right, it referred,
you know, the end was was implied. Okay, but let's say it's
not clear what you're implying. Okay, that's אינן מוכיחות. einan mochiachot. Is
that still binding? דאיתמר ידיים שאינן מוכיחות אביי אמר הויין ידיים, d’itmar
yadayim she’einan mochiachot Abaye amar havyen yadayim, it is binding, רבא אמר
לא הויין ידיים. Rava amar lo havyen yadayim. So לאביי ניחא, l’Abaye
nicha, for אביי Abaye it's good, כי יפלי is coming to include
even a יד שאינה מוכיחה. yad she’eina mochiacha. אלא לרבא מאי איכא
למימר, ela l’Rava mai ika l’meimar, what can you say for רבא?
Rava? Now I just want to pause for a minute and say
that there's a big problem with the text here because in different
גמרות, Gemarot, אביי Abaye and רבא Rava hold the opposite positions that
they're claimed to hold here. And that logically, כי יפלי, if I
told you it says איש כי יפלי, and I asked you, what
do you think that would be telling you regarding a יד שאינה
מוכיחה? yad she’eina mochiacha? If you had this פסוק, pasuk איש כי
יפלי, is it coming to tell you that it counts or that
it doesn't count? Right, you think it does because there's still some
any type of act. Okay, so it's interesting because another גמרא Gemara.
says that that well right. So it depends I guess on how
much you think the word יפלא yafli means to articulate, right? If
יפלא yafli means something like articulate and being clear about what you're
saying, you could think that the whole point of כי יפלא ki
yafli is to tell you that if it's not clear what you're
saying, it doesn't work. So that's what another גמרא Gemara says. Another
גמרא Gemara says that כי יפלא ki yafli is to say יד
שאינה מוכיח לא הוין ידיים. yad she'einah mokhiach lo havyan yadayim. So
anyways, there's a whole question about what the גירסא girsa here is.
תוספות Tosafot tries to re-read this גירסא girsa or have different גירסאות
girsaot floating around to make it consistent with other גמרות. Gemarot. To
say that איש כי יפלא ish ki yafli is excluding a יד
שאינה מוכיח, yad she'einah mokhiach, and that's lining up with the position
that says a יד שאינה מוכיח לא הוין ידיים. yad she'einah mokhiach
lo havyan yadayim. Okay, but one way or another, we think that
the איש כי יפלא ish ki yafli could be relevant to the
discussion of יד שאינה מוכיח. yad she'einah mokhiach. But it would only
be relevant to one side, whether the side is to include or
exclude is a little unclear, but it would only be relevant to
one side. So if it's not relevant, what does it come to
do? אלא לרבא מאי איכא למימר? ella le-Rava mai ika le-meimar? אלא
כי יפלא מיבעי ליה, ella ki yafli mibayei lei, and here we're
going to see why it's seen as being seen as a little
more excluding, וכדרבי טרפון, ve-khid-Rabbi Tarfon, דתניא רבי יהודה אומר משום רבי
טרפון. de-tanya Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Tarfon. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says in the name of רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, אין אחד מהם
נזיר, ein echad me-hem nazir, none of them is a נזיר, nazir,
לפי שלא ניתנה נזירות אלא להפלאה. le-fi she-lo nitnah nezirot ella le-hafla'ah.
נזירות Nezirot is only for being clear and articulate. Now what is
that case? You might remember the case of the נזירות nezirot online.
Right, right. There's this guy walking by and I say I'll be
a נזיר nazir if he's a נזיר, nazir, and somebody else says
I'll be a נזיר nazir if he's not a נזיר, nazir, and
the other guy says I'll be a נזיר nazir if one of
you is a נזיר, nazir, and the other says none of you,
it was a fun משנה, Mishnah, you might remember. Anyway, so רבי
טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says none of them is a נזיר. nazir. How
can none of them be a נזיר? nazir? So because something that
was not clear from the time you made the vow is not
good, it's not explicit, it's not articulated, it's not כי יפלא. ki
yafli. Okay, so according to רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, now you see
why כי יפלא ki yafli according to that way of thinking would
also exclude יד שאינה מוכיח. yad she'einah mokhiach. It's seen as being
demanding a greater degree of articulation. So how is that a יד?
yad? I think it's a יד מוכיח yad mokhiach because that articulation
is also not complete. Right, so yeah, so that's what I'm saying.
So according to this way of thinking, איש כי יפלא ish ki
yafli would exclude יד שאינה מוכיח yad she'einah mokhiach exactly. It could
or could include יד מוכיח, yad mokhiach, you need a פסוק pasuk.
for יד מוכיח. yad mokhiach. Oh, that's true. Okay, so then the
גמרא Gemara says like this, אלא לרבנן מאי איכא למימר, ella le-rabbanan
mai ika le-meimar, הניחא לרבי טרפון, ha nicha le-Rabbi Tarfon, אלא לרבנן
מאי איכא למימר? ella le-rabbanan mai ika le-meimar? Fine, so איש כי
יפלא ish ki yafli could be saying something about יד שאינה מוכיח,
yad she'einah mokhiach, could be saying something about רבי טרפון's Rabbi Tarfon's
position. But if you don't hold those positions, what's it coming to
tell you? אלא מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, ella mibayei lei le-khid-tanya, to tell
you the following thing. התרת נדרים פורחין באוויר ואין להם על מה
שיסמוכו. hattarat nedarim porkhin ba-avir ve-ein la-hem al mah she-yismokhu. The idea
so funny, right? It's actually a תנן, tenan, it's a משנה בחגיגה.
mishna be-Chagigah. Again, we went through all of נדרים nedarim. and all
of נזירות Nezirot and until we got to this משנה Mishnah here
quoted from a different מסכת masechet that tells us the whole idea
that you can do a התרת נדרים hattarat nedarim is really not
based on any biblical verse. Okay, now a little bit we tried
to link it to the פרשה about ראשי המטות, rashei ha-mattot, right?
לא יחל דברו, lo yakhel devaro, ואחרים מוחלים דברו. ve-acherim mokhalim devaro.
You can't sort of negate your words, other people can negate it,
but it's based on a very, the whole this whole powerful institution
that can reverse your נדר neder. is, you know, hanging on like
nothing. Now it doesn't say now there's a difference between nothing and
the other phrase in משנה חגיגה Mishnah Chagigah people might know is
הרים התלויין בשערה, harim ha-teluyin be-sa'arah, a mountain on a hairbreadth. So
you might have thought that okay this is a הרים, harim, it's
like this huge idea, you can completely reverse all of your נדרים
nedarim. and נזירות, nezirot, but it's got at least a hair, it's
got at least a פסוק pasuk of לא יחל דברו ואחרים מוחלים
אותו, lo yakhel devaro ve-acherim mokhalim oto, right? מוחלים דברו, mokhalim devaro,
you might remember that. But comes along the משנה Mishnah and says
it doesn't have anything that it's based on, no פסוק. pasuk רבי
אליעזר אומר יש להם על מה שיסמוכו. Rabbi Eliezer omer yesh la-hem
al mah she-yismokhu. No, there is something it relies on, שנאמר איש
כי יפלא, she-ne'emar ish ki yafli, כי יפלא שתי פעמים. ki yafli
shtei fe'amim. It says כי יפלא ki yafli by נזירות nezirot and
it says כי יפלא ki yafli by נדרים. nedarim? אחד הפלאה לאיסור
ואחד הפלאה להיתר. echad hafla'ah le-issur ve-echad hafla'ah le-hetter. So the same
way a speech act binds you, there can be the speech act
of the בית דין Beit Din that unbinds you. So this is
very powerful because, you know, it would have been nice if we
would have known this like, you know, four months ago, okay? Because
this conceptualizes the act of until now the act of התרת נדרים
hattarat nedarim is rooted in identifying where in hindsight you did not
really mean it or had you been thinking you wouldn't have made
it to some degree we're going to declare it to be a
טעות, ta'ut, an error, right? And that's what it's rooted in. Okay,
but then there were all these there were to some degree certain
formal requirements about that on the one hand and on the other
hand sometimes we almost didn't need you to say that I had
the error then, we just say that there was an opinion that
even if you say now I regret it, even if I didn't
regret it then, right? So this is actually coming in framing it
differently. No, there can be a formal act of a בית דין
Beit Din to basically annul it, remove it. It's not necessarily rooted
in from this way of framing it's not necessarily rooted in the
concept of טעות. ta'ut. Okay, now we know that idea from the
case of the husband and the wife. There he can be, right,
he's מיפר, meifer, he just annuls, and there it works only מכאן
ולהבא, mikan u-le-haba, it doesn't work retroactively. of like override, it's not
sort of saying it never happened, it's just annulling it from this
point onwards. A התר נדר heter neder works retroactively, but nevertheless it
seems to be working as a type of an annulment rather than
as a type of a טעות, taut, a power of a הפלאה.
hafla'ah So it's a very interesting different conceptualization, okay? So a lot
of different things we learned כי יפלי, מופלא סמוך לאיש, either by
Jews for the year before בר בת מצוה Bar Bat Mitzvah or
for non-Jews maybe they're before maybe maybe maybe any age before majority
or the reverse for non-Jews even if they are an adult whatever
that age of majority is if it exists but nevertheless we would
demand that they also that they be checked and we see that
they know what they're talking about. So again this non-formalized definition for
non-Jews, or and then other types of possible things that it is
teaching us in terms of you know in terms of what do
you call it of of new about יד מוכיח yad mochiach or
other types of needs of הפלאה and most significantly the thing at
the end about the power of התרת נדרים. hatarat nedarim. Yes. Structure
of the analysis right now seems sounds like it might be similarly
applied to קידושין kiddushin and הפקעת קידושין hafka'at kiddushin to the power
of the בית דין. Beis Din. Yeah, it's a good point, yeah,
yeah I mean because that is I mean when you talk about
annulment the most because we're influenced also by the non-Jewish world around
us like the most thing you think about is annulling marriages and
right I mean it does raise that question about what is the
power of הפקעת קידושין בית דין. hafka'at kiddushin Beis Din. Right because
if it's based on the fact that we say that when you
got married you always did it implicitly בתנאי betnai you know that
בית דין Beis Din would be okay with it, then it is
sort of similar to the טעות taut idea. But if somehow it's
something other than that just the power of בית דין Beis Din
to annul then it seems to be a different type of a
process. Okay let's look now at ס"ב עמוד ב', samech bet amud
bet, let's look at the next משנה. Mishnah. חומר בעבדים מבינשים Chomer
be'avadim mibinashim שהוא מיפר נדרי אשתו shehu meifir nidrei ishto ואינו מיפר
נדרי עבדו. ve'eino meifir nidrei avdo. Okay so there's a way in
which there's a weightiness meaning that the vow is more binding by
slaves than by women because a man can annul his wife's vow
but he cannot annul his slave's vow. Now the previous משנה Mishnah
said that he can override his slave's vow, he can כופה kofeh
force his slave to violate, okay, but he cannot force his wife
to violate. So on the one hand he can annul his wife's
vow if he does it on that day, and then by the
way even if they get divorced or whatever happens that he dies
whatever happens afterwards the vow has been the נזירות nezirut has been
ended, it's been it just it was it was annulled, okay, whereas
by a slave even if at that day he said I don't
care that you became a נזיר nazir I need you to go
ahead and this and that and the other thing, go into the
cemetery and get something for me or whatever he tells the slave,
right, and I don't care that you're a נזיר, nazir, he has
the right to do that, the slave did not have the right
to bind himself that would take away from his responsibility to his
master, but nevertheless that's an override of the נזירות, nezirut, it's not
an annulment of the נזירות. nezirut. And now if the master dies
as we're going to see or the slave he frees the slave
or whatever it is, the vow is now is now you know
he now or when the master doesn't demand that he do it
in order to in order to serve him, right, then the vow
is binding. So on the one hand and the flip side is
if he didn't annul his wife's vow and he waited a day
then he cannot tell her that she has to violate. So the
wife he can annul, the slave he can't annul, but the slave
he can force him to violate whereas the wife he cannot force
her to violate. Does the slave become טמא tamei and does he
have to do some טהרה? taharah? Yeah, yeah, so he would have
to do that whole process. Exactly, exactly. Okay. Yeah that's actually an
interesting point because on the one hand look slaves are bound by
the מצוות. mitzvos. So somehow we understand that because it's not like
I mean what does he do is he going to get lashes
like since when does listening to my master override like can my
master tell me to eat non-kosher food? Right normally you don't have
a right to force somebody to do an עבירה. aveira. Somehow what
we learn out here is that it's not that he's it's not
that it would be considered a violation because what then it becomes
is is that the slave didn't have the right to restrict himself
when he was pre-you know sort of obligated to his master in
that capacity. Okay so but on the other hand while it wouldn't
be like you know considered a violation if he became טמא tamei
presumably you're right he'd have to it'd be the reality of טומאה
tumah he'd have to bring a קרבן and start over again. I
don't know if a non-Jew can- yeah well he's not a he's
a partial Jew, he's a right exactly. Okay. So okay. ואינו מיפר-
ve'eino meifir- okay. נדרי אשתו הוא מיפר. nidrei ishto hu meifir. נדרי
עבדו- nidrei avdo- ואינו מיפר נדרי עבדו. ve'eino meifir nidrei avdo. הפר
לאשתו heifer le'ishto הפר עולמית. heifer olamit. So this is what I
already told you. If he annuls for his wife it's forever even
if he dies divorces her whatever the vow has disappeared. הפר לעבדו
heifer le'avdo by the slave it's not a real הפרה, hafarah, the
most he can do is override for the time being when he
needs the slave to serve him in a certain capacity and this
is getting in the way. So יצא לחירות משלים נזירותו. yatza lecherut
mashlim neziruto. So if the slave gets freed Then he does have
to do the full נזירות. niziros. Yes. Wait, that's different than what
you was just saying. Why? In what way? Well, because this is
saying, okay, so if the owner annuls it and then he's freed,
then the נזירות niziros kicks back in. It sounds like as long
as he's not freed it's completely not binding at all. Right. Right.
It's not that it kicks back in once he's done the errand.
Well, let's take a look. As you're right, that's not clear in
the משנה. Mishnah. Let's take a look in the גמרא. Gemara Okay.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. למה רבדו כופה לנזירות אבל לא לנדרים ולערכין.
Lama ravdo kofe leniziros aval lo lenidarim ulearchin.
So we have another question, which is, this is we have this
principle before we get to looking at our משנה Mishnah about הפרה,
hafarah, this principle that the master, which was in a previous משנה,
Mishnah, that the master can override the נזירות, niziros, right, of the
slave, well why does he have more power to override the נזירות
niziros of a slave than override another נדר neder? of the slave?
Or some of the גרסא girsa ערכין is funny, like if the
slave made a donation to the בית המקדש why could the master
override it? So some have the גרסא girsa of a שבועה, shevua,
okay? So why would he have more of a power to override
נזירות niziros than other types of things that bind and restrict the
slave, right? If you remember the גמרא Gemara yesterday quoted the פסוק
pasuk which it says לאסור איסר על נפשו, le'esor isar al nafsho,
which is not by נזירות niziros it's by a נדר. neder And
it says יצא עבד שאין נפשו קנויה לו, yatza eved she'ein nafsho
knuya lo, right? You can't bind yourself if you're pre-owned, you know
if you're owned by somebody else in that capacity. So that's by
נדרים. nedarim, So that should actually tell us that he... that if
anything the master can also override a נדר. neder Why only do
we say this by נזירות niziros and not by נדרים? nedarim Okay.
So, דאמר רחמנא לית... d'amar Rachmana leis... מאי שנא גבי נזיר דאמר
רחמנא לאסור איסר על נפשו במי שנפשו קנויה לו יצא עבד שאין
נפשו קנויה לו. maishena gabei nazir d'amar Rachmana le'esor isar al nafsho,
b'mi shenafsho knuya lo, yatza eved she'ein nafsho knuya lo. Which again,
doesn't mean it's not binding, but interestingly means it's somehow binding but
can be overridden. So אי הכי אפילו גבי נדרים נמי? i hachi
afilu gabei nedarim nami? נמי, nami, even by נדר. neder? And of
course the irony is that the whole פסוק pasuk is by נדרים,
nedarim. not by נזירות. niziros. So the logic applies to נדרים nedarim
and the פסוק pasuk applies to נדרים. nedarim So why do we
apply this principle only to a נזיר nazir and not for a
נדר? neder. אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshes, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha
bemai askinan, what are you talking about? כגון שהיה אשכול של ענבים
מונח לפניו. kegon shehaya eshkol shel anavim munach lefanav. There was a
nice cluster of grapes. גבי נדרים, Gabei nedarim, if you said this
cluster of grapes is קונם, konam, this cluster of grapes עלי, alai,
דכי נמי מיצר בהאי לא מיצר באחריני. dechi nami mitzar behai lo
mitzar beachrini. You're not forbidden in other grapes, so your master can't
tell you you gotta eat this cluster of grapes because just eat
some other grapes. So there's not a pressing need. Okay, לא מצי
כפי ליה, lo matzi kapi lei, he can't force him. גבי נזירות,
Gabei niziros, but if he were to become a נזיר, nazir, דכי
מיצר בהאי מיצר בכולהו, dechi mitzar behai mitzar bechula hu, then now
he can't eat any grapes. So מצי כפי ליה, matzi kapi lei,
he can say look I need you to eat, and you know
I need you to eat grapes and whatever, I mean this is
the food that's available and and I need you to be strong
to do my work and and there's no other option to say
well just eat some other ones. Now of course the funniest thing
is that, you know, a, what if there's other food... Okay, let's
assume the only food available is grapes. Okay. So therefore that's the
difference. But that's a very circumstantial difference, that's not a real categorical
difference, and you could have circumstances where a נדר neder does get
in the way, which is what the גמרא Gemara says. Says the
גמרא Gemara says like this: וגבי נדרים נמי לא עסקינן דליכא אלא
האי אשכול דאילו אכיל ליה חליש? u'gabei nedarim nami lo askinan d'leika
ela hai eshkol d'ilo achil lei chalish? So what? That's a very
nice constructive case, but that's not a difference between נדרים nedarim and
נזירות. niziros. You can have a case where this is the only
thing around to eat, and because of my נדר neder I am
going to get weak and not have the same strength to do
the work. It's actually in a way, if I... if you ask
me which category is more likely to get in the way of
him serving his master, נזירות niziros or נדר? neder I would totally
say נדר. neder? נזירות niziros is very limited. How often does he
have to go into a cemetery? Is it necessary for him to
cut his hair? I mean I guess if he's serving some public
role. Okay. Or is it necessary for him to drink wine or
eat grapes? But a נדר neder? could be on anything. That if
the guy said that's it I'm going vegetarian, קונם konam all meat
עלי. alai. The master could say like my example... the master could
say like what do you mean, like I need you to eat
some good red meat to have some strength to do the job
or whatever. So anyway so what type of answer is this? That
נזירות niziros gets more in the way. It's all based on the
circumstances. So the גמרא Gemara says, and now the next answer is
so funny because it's just a repeat of the first
answer. אלא אמר רבא. Ela amar Rava. So רבא Rava says, כגון
שהיה חרצן מונח לפניו. kegon shehaya chartzan munach lefanav. Let's say there
was a seeds, grape seeds in front of him. גבי נדרים Gabei
nedarim that doesn't get in the way, בהאי הוא דמיצר לא מצי
כפי ליה. behai hu de'mitzar lo matzi kapi lei. So so by
נדרים nedarim okay you don't eat grape seeds it's not getting in
the way of anything, okay, go eat something
else. But גבי נזיר דמיצר נמי באחריני בנזיר דמיצר נמי באחריני מצי
כפי ליה. gabei nazir de'mitzar nami beachrini be'nazir d'mitzar nami beachrini matzi
kapi lei. He can force him, which is crazy, all of a
sudden he needs to eat grape seeds to whatever. So the גמרא
Gemara says וגבי נדרים מי לא עסקינן דליכא אלא האי חרצן דאילו
אכיל ליה חליש? u'gabei nedarim mi lo askinan d'leika ela hai chartzan
d'ilo achil lei chalish? And so what, by נדרים nedarim who's saying
that you know you only have these grape
seeds, the you know that, דאילו אכיל ליה חליש? d'ilo achil lei
chalish? That if he wouldn't eat it he would get weak? I
mean give me a break! Right? How is נזירות nezirus getting more
in the way? You know, oh נזירות nezirus you can't eat any
grapes. So what? By נדרים nedarim there could be a case where
the נדר neder gets in the way and as it's pointed out
and תוספות Tosafot says this, and anyway, this is such this example
so much begs the question because grape seeds is not a big
restriction and a נדר neder, could get in the could more broadly
forbid you on a wide range of things. So again, נדרים nedarim
are just as much problematic, potentially getting in the way of the
עבד eved serving his master as נזירות. nezirus. So why can he
force him by נזירות nezirus and not by נדר? neder So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. אלא אמר אביי Ella amar Abaye
so says אביי. Abaye. למה רבו צריך לכפותו לנזירות? Lama rabo tzarich
lichpoto lenezirus? Why is the master need to or allowed to force
him to violate his נזירות? nezirus? ואינו צריך לכפותו לנדרים Ve'eino tzarich
lichpoto lenedarim and not for a נדר? neder ואינו צריך לכפותו לשבועה
Ve'eino tzarich lichpoto lishvua or שבועה? shvua? מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? דאמר
קרא De'amar kra להרע או להיטיב. leharei o lehaitiv. It says by
a שבועה, shvua, if a person takes an oath to do bad
or to do good. מה הטבה רשות אף הרעה רשות. Ma hatava
reshus af hara'a reshus. So the same way הטבה hatava is something
that is volitional, you like you're allowed to do it, you know
you can choose to do it or not, it has to be
a bad that you're doing by your שבועה shvua has to be
a bad that you're allowed to do. יצא להרע לאחרים שאין רשות
בידו. Yatza leharei leachairim she'ein reshus beyado. So what's a bad I'm
allowed to do? I can deny myself food. I'm hurting myself. But
I can't take a שבועה shvua that I'm going to hit Michael
here, okay, because that's hurting someone else. Okay, Michael moves away. That's
hurting someone else. So a שבועה shvua to do bad to somebody
else is not binding. Only to do bad a thing that is
a permissible bad, not a non-permissible bad. So how is that relevant?
Because he says look, so by any type of a נדר neder
if the slave does something to restrict himself, whether by a שבועה
shvua or נדר, neder he is also doing bad to other people.
Who is the other person that he is doing bad to? His
master. That's what it is though. Well, anything that is restrictive that
the master would have a a good reason to override, he doesn't
have to override because the slave fundamentally by taking it was hurting
his master's you know rights and therefore fundamentally it wasn't binding. Not
binding period. Well, I don't know if I'd say that, maybe it's
more of a rights criteria, but whatever it is he didn't have
a right he didn't have a right to do it because it
hurt his master. Okay, so by נזירות nezirus as well
it hurts his master.
So the point you know if it gets in the way. So
the answer is yeah, maybe, but we don't have a פסוק pasuk
by that. We only have a פסוק pasuk by a שבועה shvua
and we assume like שבועה shvua and נדרים nedarim. are linked this
way and not נזירות, nezirus, which is funny because נזירות nezirus is
like a subset of נדרים nedarim and נזירות nezirus is linked to
נדרים. nedarim But at the end of the day we're conceding that
circumstantially נדרים might get in the way just as much as נזירות.
nezirus. But nevertheless we have a specific פסוק by נדרים that says
it's not binding. And here's also the interesting point. להרע או להיטיב
leharei o lehaitiv tells us it's not binding at all. So in
the end, by the way, in the end, why can the master
not override a נדר and a שבועה? shvua? You know why he
can't override a נדר and a שבועה? shvua? Because he doesn't have
to. Because it wasn't binding. So it's actually quite interesting, it's the
opposite of what we thought. We thought it was binding and he
can't override, actually what we wind up learning is that a נדר
and a שבועה shvua that a slave takes that gets in the
way is not binding at all. By a נזיר nazir when it
gets in the way, right? Well, that's a question. It sounds like
to the degree that it would compromise, that's not exactly clear, right?
If it has the potential to compromise, does it not binding at
all, that's not spelled out. By a נזיר nazir we learn from
the פסוק of לאסור איסר על נפשו le'esor issar al nafsho במי
שנפשו קנויה לו, bemi shenafsho knuya lo, which by the way sounds
like a much more categorical exclusion than להרע או להיטיב. leharei o
lehaitiv. It sounds like if you are a slave and it's not
and it's not נפשו קנויה לו nafsho knuya lo fundamentally this is
not binding. That's what it sounds like. And nevertheless what we say
is it's binding but
the master can override.
As opposed to by a נדר and a שבועה shvua where we
say fundamentally it's not binding. So quite ironic and you know sort
of reversal of what we were expecting. But it's interesting we don't
find the parallel with husband and wife, בינו לבינה. beino leveina. We
could have had the same kind of construct with the עבד. eved.
Yes, so we do. In another גמרא talks about the degree to
which נזירות nezirus is something that gets in the way and is
בינו לבינה, beino leveina, but what we know by husband and wife
is that that translates into the right to be מפר meifer as
opposed to by the עבד eved where it translates into the right
to override, right? So so that's the difference. Okay, let's just try
we might as well I think we can do next four minutes
get to the bottom of the page. מכנגד פניו, Mikneged panav, let's
say the slave ran away. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, I
mean literally it actually means ran away, might strictly not in the
presence of the master, but let's say it means ran away. רבי
מאיר אומר לא ישתה, Rabbi Meir omer lo yishte, in that case
he can't drink, okay, he is bound by his נזירות nezirus when
he's not in the presence of his master. רבי יוסי אומר ישתה,
Rabbi Yose omer yishte, he can drink. So גמרא says what's the
debate? So לימא בדישמואל קמיפלגי, Leima bid'Shmuel kamiflegi, maybe they debate שמואל's
Shmuel ruling? דאמר שמואל De'amar Shmuel המפקיר עבדו יצא לחירות ואין צריך
גט שחרור. Hamafkir avdo yatza lecherus ve'ein tzarich get shichrur. Once the
master loses monetary ownership over his slave, the slave automatically like he's
mafkir it, he renounces. רבי יוסי אומר ישהא קמיה. Rabbi Yose omer
yeshei kamei. So the גמרא says what's the debate? So לימא בדשמואל
קמיפלגי, leima bid'Shmuel kamifligi, maybe they debate שמואל's Shmuel ruling? דאמר שמואל,
de'amar Shmuel, המפקיר עבדו יצא לחירות ואין צריך גט שיחרור. hamifkir avdo
yatza lecherut ve'ein tzarich get shichrur. Once the master loses monetary ownership
over his slave, the slave automatically, like he's מפקיר mafkir it, he
renounces his monetary ownership, the slave's personal status automatically changes. This is
a question about a slave, right? He's on the one hand he's
property, and on the other hand his personal status is he's not
a full Jew, he's a, you know, he's a slave. So to
what degree are they linked? So שמואל Shmuel says they're linked. If
you don't own him anymore, he automatically changes his personal status and
he does not need a גט שיחרור, get shichrur, a writ of
manumission. So, maybe that's the debate. Now we're assuming if the slave
ran away, it meant that the master therefore either was מפקיר mafkir
it, or implicitly he doesn't expect that the slave will ever come
back, it's a type of a יאוש, ye'ush, it's like a הפקר.
hefker. So רבי מאיר אית ליה דשמואל, Rabbi Meir islei d'Shmuel, רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir holds like שמואל Shmuel and therefore says the slave
is now a free man, and therefore he's bound by his נזירות.
nezirut. ורבי יוסי לית ליה דשמואל, ve'Rabbi Yose laislei d'Shmuel, רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose doesn't hold of it. So maybe that's the debate. The
גמרא says no, not necessarily. דכולי עלמא אית להו דשמואל, d'kulei alma
islei d'Shmuel, everybody could hold like שמואל, Shmuel, that if he really
was being, if the master really was מפקיר mafkir him, then really
did renounce his monetary ownership, maybe he would be free and then
obviously it would be binding. אלא מאן דאמר ישתה, ela man d'amar
yishteh, but here it's not a case that the master renounced the
ownership. The master might be still hoping that the slave he captures
the slave or the slave comes back. So מאן דאמר ישתה man
d'amar yishteh סבר סוף סוף מהדר הדר ואתי לגבי. savar sof sof
mehadar hadar ve'ati gabei. So the slave ultimately he's expected that the
slave will come back or he'll capture the slave one way or
the other, and therefore since he's coming back to me, לישקי חמרא
כי היכי דלא לכחוש, lishki chamra ke'heichi d'lo likhush, it's right now
I want him to drink because his drinking is not getting in
the way of, you know, of me, I'm sorry, I want him
to drink because right, meaning the נזירות nezirut shouldn't be binding, should
be overridden because I want him to drink so that he still
has, so he still has strength if I ever recapture him. So
the same way when he's with me I want him to drink
so that he has strength and it overrides the נזירות, nezirut, even
when he ran away I want him to drink so he stays
strong. Okay? So the same way the override applies when he's with
me, the override applies when he's away because it helps keeps him
strong and I'm expecting to get him back. ולמאן דאמר לא ישתה,
u'le'man d'amar lo yishteh, the more interesting one is רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir that says that the נזירות nezirut is binding when he runs
away, the override doesn't apply anymore, סבר ליהוי ליה צערא כי היכי
דלהדר לגבי. savar lihavy leh tzara ke'heichi d'lahadar gabei. No, now דוקא
davka I want the נזירות nezirut to be binding and I want
him to be restricted, so he'll think, oh, if I go back
I'll be able to drink wine. So basically everybody agrees that the
master has not renounced ownership and the question is, is it in
the master's interest when the slave has run away for the נזירות
nezirut to remain binding or not remain binding? Do we assume the
override, because the whole point of the override is just serve the
master's interest? So what do we assume the master's interests are when
the slave is in the field? I'm going to just take these
other questions. Yeah. Please, one, he's another, he took a vow to
be a נזיר, nazir, so why would he come back in order
to drink wine? Yeah, that's a good point. Yes. That might be
self-defeating. Okay, yeah. Michael. The other thing is I guess that would
depend on whether he's בורח bore'ach from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to
חוצה לארץ. Chutz La'Aretz. All right, that's a different problem. All right.
What if we say that the master is, like, that interest is
not, is it or is it not—